All right, now that you've built your
first web page, it's time to learn how
to use the developer tools. So, this
video is going to be for anyone who's
using a Chromiumbi based browser. So,
basically, if you're using Google
Chrome, Firefox, Microsoft Edge, most
popular browsers, um your chances are
you're using a Chromiumbased browser. So
the way you access your developer tools
on a chromium based browser is you'll
click on the screen and you'll hit
command option I if you're on a Mac or
you'll hit control shift I if you're on
a Windows. The other way you can access
it is you can double click or right
click if you're on a Windows into the
center of the window and you can click
inspect and that will pop up this tab
right here. Um, for most of you, this
tab was probably docked to the right
hand panel like this when you first
viewed it. I don't like mine there, so I
like to move it to the bottom. The way
you do that is you'll click these three
dots right here, and then I will dock it
to the bottom. And now my developer
tools are where I want them. So, let's
talk about the different tabs. Let me
zoom in real quick on my console. All
right. So, the first tab that we're
going to talk about is the elements tab.
Here in the elements tab, you can see it
actually pulled in our HTML exactly as
we typed it. And as we hover around,
you'll see that it highlights on screen
the part of the HTML that we're hovering
over. We use the elements tab when we're
trying to understand how our HTML is
working and how our CSS is working. So,
if we open up the body tag, we can
actually edit this on the live website
and see what changes would look like.
This won't actually change the code, but
it'll allow us to test code without
having to constantly flip back and forth
between windows. So, what I'm going to
do here is I'm going to just change
hello world, and I'm going to double
click into it, and I'm going to change
it to say hello
um moon. And then as soon as I click
off, you can see it updated on screen.
If I reload the page, it goes back to
the original HTML that we wrote. And so
I was able to test some HTML really
quickly and just determine if that
solved my problem. That is the main
reason you'll use the elements tab. We
probably won't use the elements tab a
lot in this course because this is a
JavaScript course and not an HTML or CSS
course. But I wanted you to be aware
that this tab was here. The tab where we
will spend most of our time is the
console tab. So this here is your
console. And in here you can type
whatever you want. This is where all of
your JavaScript errors are going to show
up. So, if you write code that doesn't
work and you don't know why it's not
working, the console tab is the best tab
to check. So, I'm just going to type a
bunch of gibberish and hit enter and it
says uncaught reference error. And if
you don't understand what that means,
don't worry. I'm just showing you that
there. This is a place where you will
see errors with your code. It's also a
place where you can test your
JavaScript. So, if I want to test my
JavaScript skills, if you think back to
the video where I talked about what
programming is, I showed you how to type
the hello world message in JavaScript.
I'm going to just type that line right
here, right now. And it's going to say
console.log
and then in parenthesis. I'm going to
type hello world. Close parenthes close
my quotation marks, close my
parenthesis, and hit enter. And you'll
see that as soon as I did this, it said
console.log log hello world and right
below where I typed that code, it wrote
the message hello world. If you were
following along, you have successfully
written your first JavaScript.
Congratulations. Um, so the main reasons
we use the console is to find our
JavaScript errors and to test
JavaScript.
On the sources tab, we're not going to
talk much about this. I want you to be
aware of it because when we get to
debugging, this is a tab you'll want to
look at. but it basically just shows you
all of the files that are associated
with your project. And we will use this
a lot more when we get to the debugging
section. Um, the last tab I want to show
you is the network tab. And for this
tab, I do need to expand the window a
bit. But when you reload your page, your
network tab will show you all of the
files that your computer requested to
run this page. So, if you are requesting
styles for the page, if you're
requesting images for the page, if
you're requesting videos for the page,
all of them will show up here.
Um, and the main thing to notice here is
the status codes. If you've taken a
course that talks about status codes,
fantastic. If you haven't taken a course
that talks about status codes, the thing
I want you to remember is red equals
bad. So the network tab is what I use
when something isn't loading properly on
my page. So if I've written a website
and then an image isn't loading, then
I'll come over here to the network tab
and make sure that it doesn't highlight
the image in red. If it's highlighted
the image in red, it means it cannot
find my image and I need to locate that
image so that it can show up on the
website. Um, so for the network tab, you
use it if something isn't loading on
your website. For the sources tab, you
use it for when you're debugging. For
the console tab, it's where you're going
to see all of your error messages and
it's where you can test your JavaScript.
And for the elements tab, it's when you
want to test your HTML and your CSS and
you want to understand how the page is
set up. I hope that helps you understand
the developer tools. Thanks for
watching.